Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
Uncommon Knowledge video tapes
1996-2010
2001C109
Hoover Institution Archives
124 manuscript boxes, 3 card file boxes, 54 videotape reels, digital files (56.6 linear feet)
Relates to various aspects of American foreign and domestic policy. Television program sponsored by the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired between 2001 and 2011. For the broadcast years, most of the videotapes and audio tapes were acquired directly from the Uncommon Knowledge production staff in a series of increments. Some tapes were obtained from storage at the Hoover Press. Additional videotapes were acquired from the Bay Area Video Coalition in San Francisco, California and the PBS Media Library in Alexandria, Virginia in 2009. For the webcast years, video programs are received directly from Stanford Video. Transcripts were captured from various websites by Hoover Archives staff. Transcripts were captured by Hoover Archives staff from the Uncommon Knowledge website (http://www.hoover.org/multimedia/uk/) and the Internet Archive's Wayback Machine since December 2008. Uncommon Knowledge is still being broadcast; video will continue to be deposited at the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Archival Materials note
Peter Robinson papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
Uncommon Knowledge is a public policy talk show produced by the Hoover Institution. It features Hoover research fellow Peter M. Robinson discussing national and international economic, political, and social issues with political leaders, distinguished scholars, leading journalists, and others. William F. Buckley Jr. designated it as the successor to his television program, Firing Line.
Uncommon Knowledge was broadcast as a weekly half-hour television program from 1996 to June 2005. The first four seasons were broadcast on KTEH-TV, a Public Broadcasting Service (PBS) affiliate in San Jose, California; beginning with the Winter/Spring 2000 season it was carried by PBS stations throughout the United States. It was also carried internationally by National Public Radio (NPR) Worldwide.
Beginning in 2006, Uncommon Knowledge became an exclusive on the web, offered through National Review Online, FORA.tv, and the Hoover Institution website. The unedited webcasts are typically between 30 and 40 minutes in duration.
During the broadcast years, each program in the season was assigned a sequential number, and with each new season, the numbering started with the next even hundred:
1996: 1-13
1997: 101-113
Winter 1998: 201-213
1998-1999: 301-326
1999-2000: 401-426
2000-2001: 501-539
2001-2002: 601-639
2002-2003: 701-739
2003-2004: 801-839
2004-2005: 901-939
After the program shifted to webcasting, the PBS program numbering was discontinued and Hoover Archives staff assigned each program a sequential number:
2006: WUK06 01-04
2007: WUK07 01-10
2008: WUK08 01-24
2009: WUK09 01-25
2010: WUK10 01-25
Host Peter M. Robinson writes about business and politics, and edits the Hoover Institution's quarterly journal, the Hoover Digest. He has written three books: How Ronald Reagan Changed My Life (Regan Books, 2003); It's My Party: A Republican's Messy Love Affair with the GOP (Warner Books, 2000); and the best-selling business book Snapshots from Hell: The Making of an MBA (Warner Books, 1994; still available in paperback).
In 1979, he graduated summa cum laude from Dartmouth College, where he majored in English. He went on to study politics, philosophy, and economics at Oxford University, graduating in 1982. Robinson spent six years in the White House, serving from 1982 to 1983 as chief speechwriter to Vice President George H. W. Bush and from 1983 to 1988 as special assistant and speechwriter to President Ronald Reagan. He wrote the historic Berlin Wall address in which President Reagan called on General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev to "tear down this wall!"
After the White House, Robinson attended the Stanford University Graduate School of Business, where the journal he kept formed the basis for Snapshots from Hell. He graduated with an MBA in 1990. He then spent a year in New York City with Fox Television, reporting to the owner of the company, Rupert Murdoch. He spent a second year in Washington, D.C., with the Securities and Exchange Commission, where he served as the director of the Office of Public Affairs, Policy Evaluation, and Research. In 1993, Robinson joined the Hoover Institution.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes videorecordings, audio recordings, and transcripts of programs. Most recordings represent edited programs, though a few of the webcasts are unedited. Unedited webcast versions do not have lower third graphics (name/title) nor a Hoover watermark, and have a 4:3 aspect ratio (vs. 16:9 pillarbox for edited shows). Videotape formats in the collection include VHS, Betacam SP, Digital Betacam, one-inch videotape, D3, DVCAM, miniDV, and DVD. Sound recording formats are limited to audio CD. Transcripts are file-based (RTF or PDF).
Full descriptions of all programs are taken verbatim from the Uncommon Knowledge website. Dates listed for each program are the date the program was taped. Where the Uncommon Knowledge web site information differs from the label on a video tape, the label information has been used.
The two Collections of Programs series consist of programs grouped around particular themes by the Uncommon Knowledge staff.
The one-inch videotapes usually contain more than one program per reel. For unidentified programs, the information in the container list is taken from the labels on the videotapes. They may contain clips from multiple programs.
The Program Transcripts series is not quite complete. Transcripts through 2008 were captured by Hoover Archives staff from the Uncommon Knowledge website ( http://www.hoover.org/multimedia/uk/) and the Internet Archive's Wayback Machine ( http://www.archive.org/web/web.php) from December 2008 to January 2009. When searching the Wayback Machine, the following URLs were used: http://www-hoover.stanford.edu and http://www.hoover.stanford.edu.
Because Uncommon Knowledge is an ongoing program, additional material continues to be added to the collection.
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; United States--Foreign relations--1989-; United States--Politics and government--1989-; Video tapes.
- Program transcripts, 24 February 1997 - 1 December 2009 (Folder Reading room workstation)
  Scope and Contents note
  Transcripts of Uncommon Knowledge programs, which typically also include the program title, date taped, brief description that sets up the program, name and description of guests. Transcripts for 1996 are not available, and a few transcripts are missing from other seasons. Dates used are the date the program was taped
- Research Materials for Individual Programs (Folder 61-62)
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 1, 1996
    - "Drug Decriminalization" No. UK1_1, 1996 May 18 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Joseph McNamara and Edwin Meese III
    - "104th Congress" No. UK1_2, 1996 May 25 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf)
      William Kristol and Nelson Polsby
    - "China " No. UK1_3, 1996 June 1 (Folder VHS, box 1; Betacam SP, box 27)
      George P. Shultz
    - "Preferential Policies" No. UK1_4, 1996 June 29 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Shelby Steele
    - "Bosnia " No. UK1_5, 1996 July 6 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf)
    - "School Choice" No. UK1_6, 1996 July 13 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Henry Levin and Terry Moe
    - "Strategic Defense Initiative" No. UK1_7, 1996 July 20 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Sidney Drell and Edward Teller
    - "Migrations and Cultures" No. UK1_8, 1996 July 27 (Folder VHS, box 1)
      Thomas Sowell
    - "Future Trends in Russian Politics" No. UK1_9, 1996 August 3 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      John Dunlop and Martin Malia
    - "Can there Be Peace in the Middle East?" No. UK1_10, 1996 August 10 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Charles Hill and Abraham Sofaer
    - "American Exceptionalism" No. UK1_11, 1996 August 17 (Folder VHS, box 1)
      Seymour Martin Lipset
    - "Shifting the Political Landscape in America" No. UK1_12, 1996 September 14 (Folder VHS, box 1; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      David Brady and Douglas Rivers
    - "The Changing Role of the United Nations" No. UK1_13, 1996 September 21 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Charles Hill and Stephen Stedman
  - Series 100, 1997
    - "Deficit Disorder: The Balanced Budget Amendment" No. UK101, 1997 April 5 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Martin Anderson, fellow, Hoover Institution, and John Ellwood, University of California, Berkeley, discuss the balanced budget amendment.
    - "Aging: From Baby Boom to Bust" No. UK102, 1997 April 12 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      John Shoven, professor of economics and dean of the School of Humanities and Science, Stanford University, and David Wise, fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss demographics, social security, health care, and retirement savings.
    - "Red Flag over Hong Kong" No. UK103, 1997 April 19 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Lawrence Lau, professor, Stanford University, and Alvin Rabushka, fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss the impact of China assuming control of Hong Kong on July 1.
    - "Rich Get Richer" No. UK104, 1997 May 10 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Kenneth Arrow, professor of economics, Stanford University, and Nobel laureate and Kenneth Judd, fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss the sources of the persistent and increasing inequality of American incomes.
    - "Reading, Writing, and Reform" No. UK105, 1997 May 17 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Maureen DiMarco, former secretary, Office of Child Development and Education, California, and Bill Honig, former superintendent of public instruction, California, discuss the problems with America's classrooms and how to fix them.
    - "The One Percent Solution? " No. UK106, 1997 February 24 (Folder Betacam SP, box 27)
      Michael Boskin and David Brady, fellows, Hoover Institution, discuss why it's important to adjust the CPT now and whether it's politically possible to do so.
    - "Fundamentally Speaking" No. UK107, 1997 June 7 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Laurence Iannaccone, professor of economics, University of Santa Clara, and Guity Nashat, fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss Islamic Fundamentalism and what Islamic Fundamentalists want.
    - "Point, Click...Censorship" No. UK108, 1997 April 7 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Ned Desmond, editor, Infoseek; Mike Godwin, staff counsel, Electronic Frontier; and Virginia Postrel, editor, Reason, discuss the Communications Decency Act. Desmond, Godwin, and Postrel debate the constitutionality of the law, and more broadly, what role the federal government should have in regulating the web.
    - "Political Tectonics" No. UK109, 1997 June 21 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      David Brady, fellow, Hoover Institution, and Nelson Polsby, professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley, discuss the implications of Republican Houses of Congress and a Democratic president
    - "Lock 'em Up?" No. UK110, 1997 June 28 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Lance Izumi, Pacific Research Institute, and Joe McNamara, fellow, Hoover Institution, debate the following questions: Are states failing to lock up enough criminals for long enough? Is prison incarceration a cost-effective strategy for fighting crime? Does a higher incarceration rate deter crime?
    - "Farewell, Welfare" No. UK111, 1997 April 23 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Thomas MaCurdy, fellow, Hoover Institution, and Eugene Smolensky, chair, department of public policy, University of California, Berkeley, discuss President Clinton's welfare reform legislation.
    - "British Elections" No. UK112, 1997 May 25 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Jerry Dorfman, fellow, Hoover Institution, and Kenneth Garcia, staff writer, San Francisco Chronicle, discuss the Labor Party's victory in the national election. What does a Labor Party victory mean for Great Britain, and do British domestic politics matter to the United States?
    - "Brave New World Order" No. UK113, 1997 May 21 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Coit Blacker, senior fellow, Institute for International Studies and Michael McFaul, fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss a host of issues confronting a new Europe. Should American soldiers be willing to defend Poland? Russia? Does a crumbling Russia pose a threat to the United States?
  - Series 200, 1998 Winter
    - "On Guard" No. UK201, 1997 October 23 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      William Perry, former secretary of defense and senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and George Shultz, former secretary of state and distinguished fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss the threats we face as a nation and what should be done about them.
    - "National Insecurity" No. UK202, 1997 October 23 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      William Perry, former secretary of defense and senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and George Shultz, former secretary of state and distinguished fellow, Hoover Institution, continue their discussion on the threats and challenges facing the United States in a post-cold war world.
    - "Habla English?" No. UK203, 1997 October 23 (Folder VHS, box 2; 1", on shelf)
      Joseph Jaramillo, staff attorney, Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, and Ron Unz, Chairman, English for the Children, discuss if bilingual education failed and if it should be improved or eliminated.
    - "This Land Is My Land...Isn't It?" No. UK204, 1997 October 31 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf)
      Terry Anderson, director, Political Economy Research Center and fellow, Hoover Institution, and Carl Pope, executive director, Sierra Club, take on environmental controversies from around the country.
    - "Cybersnoops" No. UK205, 1997 October 21 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      David Friedman, professor of law, University of Santa Clara, and Edwin Meese III, former United States attorney general and distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution, discuss how we balance the rights of our citizens with the very real needs of national security.
    - "Gen X Files" No. UK206, 1997 October 31 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Kellyanne Fitzpatrick, founder and president, the Polling Company, and David Serrano-Sewell, special assistant to the mayor of San Francisco, discuss generation-X, the 50 million Americans born between 1965 and 1978 and their attitudes toward government and politics.
    - "Curtains for Windows?" No. UK207, 1997 December 19 (Folder 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 27)
      Rich Karlgaard, editor, Forbes ASAP Magazine and Gary Reback, partner, Wilson Sonsini Goodrich Rosati, examine the Department of Justice charges that Microsoft is violating anti-trust laws by keeping competitors out of the market, stifling technological innovation, and denying consumers a choice of products.
    - "They're Coming to America" No. UK208, 1997 November 13 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Peter Brimlow, author, Alien Nation and media fellow, Hoover Institution, and David Kennedy, professor of history, Stanford University, air their divergent opinions on immigration.
    - "Follow the Money" No. UK209, 1997 November 13 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Annelise Anderson, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution; Tony Miller, founder, Californians for Political Reform Foundation; and Carol Wagner Vallianos, member, board of directors, the League of Women Voters, tackle campaign finance, an issue the politicians would rather not touch.
    - "Lost in Space?" No. UK210, 1997 December 11 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Timothy Ferris, professor of journalism, University of California, Berkeley; Andrew Fraknoi, chair, department of astronomy, Foothill College; and David Morrison, director of space, NASA Ames Research Center, wonder what we are doing in space and how the public is served by the billions we continue to spend.
    - "Red Tide Rising. " No. UK211, 1997 December 11 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Arnold Beichman, research fellow, Hoover Institution; Lawrence Lau, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and professor of economics, Stanford University; and Mike Oksenberg, senior fellow, Asia/Pacific Research Center, Stanford University, acknowledge that China wants to be counted among the world's powers. Is China on its way to becoming "the" super power? Should the United States be worried? Should we respond? Are the U.S. and China on a collision course?
    - "The Heat Is On" No. UK212, 1997 December 19 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Donald Aiken, senior scientist, Union of Concerned Scientists; David Goldstein, senior scientist, energy, National Resources Defense Council; and Henry Rowen, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and director, Asia/Pacific Research Center, discuss the effects of the December 1997 treaty agreeing to cut its greenhouse gas emissions seven percent below 1990 levels by the year 2012.
    - "A House Divided" No. UK213, 1997 October 21 (Folder 1", on shelf)
      Clayborne Carson, director, Martin Luther King Papers Project, Stanford University, and Stephen Thernstrom, coauthor, America in Black and White: One Nation Indivisible, sharply disagree on affirmative action and offer radically differing views on one of the most divisive issues in American Society.
  - Series 300, 1998-1989
    - "Up in Smoke: The War on Tobacco" No. UK301, 1998 October 3 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28)
      David E. Bonfilio, volunteer, American Cancer Society; James W. Stratton, deputy director of prevention services, Department of Health Services, California; and Jacob Sullum, senior editor, Reason Magazine and author, For Your Own Good: The Anti Smoking Crusade and the Tyranny of Public Health, discuss the war against tobacco. Are public health advocates asking the federal government to overstep its bounds, or is it time for a national tobacco policy?
    - "Nowhere to Run, Nowhere to Hide: Bioterrorism" No. UK302, 1998 October 10 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28; D3, box 53;)
      Abraham D. Sofaer, the George P. Shultz senior fellow, Hoover Institution; Jonathan B. Tucker, director, chemical/biological weapons nonproliferation project, Center for Nonproliferation Studies; and Dean Wilkening, director, science program, Center for International Security and Arms Control, Stanford University, discuss whether the United States is prepared for a biological or chemical weapons attack. Is it possible that we are over-hyping the threat, scaring the American public, and allowing the Federal Bureau of Investigation to further extend their already-broad powers into our personal lives? Re-aired as UK428
    - "It's All Foreign to Me: Clinton Administration Foreign Policy" No. UK303, 1998 October 17 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28)
      Coit Blacker, senior fellow, Institute for International Studies, Stanford University; Gloria Duffy, chief executive officer, Commonwealth Club, California; and Charles Hill, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution, put the Clinton record to the test--how has the administration fared on the host of threats and challenges facing the U.S. from Saddam Hussein to Boris Yeltsin, from China to India and Pakistan
    - "Show Me the Money: The Minimum Wage Debate" No. UK304, 1998 October 24 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28)
      Shirley Burnell, board member, ACORN; Michael Hawkins, president, California Restaurant Association; Thomas MaCurdy, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and professor of economics, Stanford University; and Eduardo Rosario, executive officer, San Francisco Labor Council, AFL-CIO, pose the question: Is another increase in the minimum wage good for the economy? Or is the real issue over whether there should be a minimum wage at all?
    - "Media Circus: The State of the Media" No. UK305, 1998 October 31 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28)
      James Risser, professor, department of communication, director of John S. Knight fellowship program, and director of the graduate program in journalism, Stanford University, and Robert Zelnick, media fellow, Hoover Institution, ask whether the press today is driven by the "public's right to know" or pressure to beat the competition.
    - "Jury on Trial: Reforming the Criminal Justice System" No. UK306, 1998 November 14 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28; D3, box 53;)
      Susan Estrich, Robert Kingsley professor of law and political science, University of Southern California; Charles L. Hobson, attorney, Criminal Justice Legal Foundation; and Pamela Karlan, professor of law, Stanford University, take a critical look at justice in America and tell how to fix a system badly in need of repair. Re-aired as UK429
    - "Playing Hardball: The Best Way to Fight and Deter Crime" No. UK307, 1998 November 21 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28; D3, box 53; as UK430; Betacam SP, box 32)
      Susan Estrich, Robert Kingsley professor of law and political science, University of Southern California; Charles L. Hobson, attorney, Criminal Justice Legal Foundation; and Pamela Karlan, professor of law, Stanford University, give a lively presentation of different approaches to stopping crime. Fed up with crime, the public has demanded "get tough" laws, locking up more criminals, handing out longer sentences and calling for more executions. Is it working? Re-aired as UK430
    - "It Ain't Over till It's Over: U.S.-Russia Relations after the Cold War" No. UK308, 1998 December 5 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28)
      Brian Hall, contributor, New York Times Magazine and Michael McFaul, Peter and Helen Bing research fellow, Hoover Institution and assistant professor of political science, Stanford University, pose the question: Is the cold war really over? Is our strategic weapons policy in line with Ronald Reagan's proclamation that "a nuclear war cannot be won and must never be fought?"
    - "Semper Fidel? The Cuban Embargo" No. UK309, 1998 December 12 (Folder VHS, box 3; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 28)
      William Ratliff, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution, and Jose Sorzano, former president of the Cuban-American National Foundation, discuss whether isolating Castro is still effective. The Clinton administration argues that isolating Castro is the best way to make him democratize, adopt market reforms, and compensate Americans for property seized during the revolution. Is it?